Upwork, one of the biggest
freelancer platforms in the world.
Now, it's struggling.
Revenue is flat, their market cap has collapsed
86%, from 7.5 billion to barely 1 billion.
Now they're laying off mass amounts of staff.
And it's entirely Upwork's own fault.
What happens when you keep stacking
more and more fees on freelancers?
When you try to squeeze your most loyal
users for everything they have.
This is the fall of Upwork.
While remote work may be normal
today, in the 2010s, people were
still figuring out how to make it work.
Freelancers and clients had to learn how
to adapt workplace culture to relationships
built entirely through a screen. How do you
manage someone not in the office? How do you
know they did work 10 hours and not just 2?
To solve this, Elance-oDesk,
before it was called Upwork,
introduced features like hourly tracking,
activity logs, and periodic screenshots,
as many as 6 times an hour.
This sounds annoying… and it was,
But it did have a purpose.
"I've only ever had one client fight
me on hours and I won because those screen caps
showed I was actively working on their project."
"I don't mind a client being able to
see my screen; if I were billing a
client without the tool it would be
their project on my screen anyway,"
But, this doesn't work for everyone,
and there were security concerns.
One thing drew every freelancer in, a flat
fee of 10% for any work done on the platform.
Pretty great.
But, it wouldn't last.
In May 2016, CEO Stéphane Kasriel announced
a new payment system: the sliding fee.
Instead of the standard 10% commission,
freelancers would now pay 20% on their
first $500 with a client, 10% from
$500 to $10,000, and 5% above that.
At first, it didn't sound so bad, and
to some it would even be a discount.
The longer a freelancer worked with
a client, the less they would pay.
But there was a problem.
Most jobs on Upwork were
short-term gigs: fixing a website, designing
social media posts, writing a script.
As a result, many freelancers never earned enough
from a single client to escape the 20% tier.
But this was just the beginning.
Upwork also introduced a 2.75% processing fee
on client payments, meaning the platform was now
taking a cut from both sides of the transaction.
Sounds small, but that's on the entire job.
Imagine a company spends $100,000 hiring
freelancers through Upwork. This processing
fee would add another $2,750 in costs.
Not to mention the new monthly
subscription fees clients had to pay.
This weird dynamic spilled into
client-freelancer relationships.
Freelancers raised their rates to offset the
fees. Clients pushed back to keep costs down.
Not because of the value of the
job and the work, but because of
Upwork's strange fee system playing both sides.
The backlash was immediate but Upwork doubled
down, saying "While it's never easy to make a
big change like this, we decided it was time
to take this step to make Upwork an even better
place for professional freelancers and clients."
Upwork wasn't budging. And why would they?
Revenue was booming.
Remote work was becoming more and more
popular, and people were beginning to notice.
So, on October 2, 2018, Upwork went
public. Its IPO was priced at $15 per
share for roughly 12.5 million shares. The stock
opened at $23, a 53% jump and closed at $21.18,
up 41% on its first day.
The IPO raised $187 million.
This was a huge success but also
introduced another long-term problem.
Upwork now had investors to please and
had to figure out how to extract even
more cash from freelancers.
So came another change,
arguably worse than the first: Connects.
Connects are, basically, virtual tokens
freelancers must spend to submit proposals.
A free account received about 10 per month,
barely enough to apply for a single job,
as many listings required between 7 and
25 Connects just to click "Apply."
Before this, you could send unlimited
proposals to clients.
Now these Connects are
sold in bundles of 10 for $1.61.
Freelancers were competing against
others who could spend extra Connects
to boost their proposals to the top.
In other words, you were paying for the privilege
of applying to jobs you might never get.
And, it gets even worse.
Over the years, the number
of Connects required kept climbing.
For freelancers, income was now being
cut from multiple directions: Connects
to bid on jobs, service fees on earnings,
and withdrawal fees to access their money.
As if that wasn't enough, the 60 free monthly
Connects were cut, with new freelancers getting
just 20. Each Connect was priced at $0.15.
But just like the job fee,
this was framed as a benefit.
[Jessica Tiwari, VP of product]: "I actually
do not believe that this change will make it
harder for new freelancers,"
There is some logic to this.
This means fewer submissions to clients, and
those clients, according to Upwork, had "expressed
feeling overwhelmed by the number of proposals
they received in response to a posted project".
"Upwork said that on average, most freelancers
will spend about $5 or less per month on Connects,
but the company didn't provide details
on how it calculated that figure."
[Upwork]: "With paid Connects, we expect
freelancers will submit fewer proposals,
increasing your likelihood of winning
projects and making it easier for clients to
identify high-quality talent."
But to many users, it felt like
job hunting itself had become expensive,
and a way for Upwork to extract revenue.
Imagine if Indeed charged you
for every job you applied to?
Then, things just got better
and better… for Upwork at least.
The pandemic sent remote work into the mainstream.
With COVID-19, 12% of the U.S.
workforce began freelancing,
but among Gen Z workers aged 18 to 22, nearly
half entered freelance work during the pandemic.
At least, according to a study by
Upwork, so take it with a grain of salt.
But there's no doubt freelance
platforms were booming.
Revenue in financial year 2019 climbed to $300
million, then to 370 million, then to 500 million.
By July 13, 2021, the stock had surged to $60.70.
With no end of remote work growth in sight,
despite all the anger and frustration
from freelancers, what could go wrong?
Quite a lot, actually. Especially
when you consider something else:
Upwork wasn't making any profit.
And boy, they weren't close to it either.
To attempt to get there, Upwork was about to start
squeezing freelancers for everything they had.
While Upwork was reporting record numbers, the
backlash over its growing fees was still brewing.
Pandemic-driven demand was so
strong, it seemed that the anger
over fees never dented growth.
But it would show up soon enough.
In the meantime, Upwork was
giving that anger plenty of fuel.
On April 26, 2023, Upwork seemed to listen.
The flat 10% commission was reintroduced.
The 20/10/5 tiers were scrapped.
Wait, was Upwork actually listening now?
Were they cutting down on the fees?
It's a bit more complicated.
Before the change, a $500 project incurred
a 20% fee, or $100. Under the new flat 10%
system, that same project cost just $50.
For a new freelancer, this was great news.
They kept more of what they earned.
But it doubled the fee on the
platform's best freelancers.
The 5% reward for building a long,
high-value client relationship was gone.
Under the new system, freelancers who had
already crossed the $10,000 threshold were
pushed back to a flat 10%, instead of 5%.
So, it punished Upwork's most
important customer: their loyal
freelancers, who, needless to say, felt cheated.
Their cost to Upwork literally doubled overnight,
because Upwork was feeling the pressure.
After reporting a loss of $89.9 million in 2022,
Upwork was keen to "significantly accelerate
[their] progress toward long-term profitability".
They were cutting brand spend, streamlining the
business, and of course, trying to increase fees.
They concluded that "the bulk of money made on the
platform is made by the top rated, expert-vetted
freelancers and agencies, and it may not be most
profitable for Upwork to charge a lower service
fee to these high-tier freelancers"
But it gets worse.
They added a $4.95 fee which was charged every
time a new contract was created. It did not matter
whether the job was a $50 gig or a $500 gig.
Though this was from the client's side.
But we're not even done.
In 2025, Upwork changed the rules again.
The flat 10% fee was gone.
Yes! Again!
But what replaced it was
possibly the worst of all.
A variable fee ranging from 0% to
15%, set by a hidden algorithm.
Essentially, Upwork replaced
a predictable commission with
dynamic pricing. The fee now depended
on factors like supply and demand,
competition in your skill category,
and overall market conditions.
The fee also wasn't even shown
until you submitted a proposal.
That's right. You didn't even know how much you
were paying, or what your profit margins were.
Not only is it greedy, but the lack of
transparency is extremely confusing.
And once assigned, that percentage
was locked in for the entire contract.
(From post): "Upwork claims this will "balance"
the marketplace by tweaking fees based on supply,
demand, complexity, and a bunch of
vague factors. Translation? If you
work in a competitive category, expect to
be taxed for the privilege of existing."
Two people doing similar jobs could
still be charged different percentages,
depending on how the algorithm classifies them.
This also made recommending Upwork
difficult, because no one really knew
how much they'd be making.
And it gets weirder.
High-demand skills may even qualify for 0%. Sounds
great, but very few would actually get this.
And of course, it was Upwork's
black box deciding all this.
On the outside this was advertised as "The
0% commission" as high-demand skills may
qualify for a 0% commission rate.
While it advertises 0% rates,
most freelancers still pay around
10–15%, often without knowing why.
Just imagine trying to manage your
work, clients, and make any profit,
with a platform making all of these changes.
Or imagine seeing one of these announced
changes and thinking "Oh great! Fewer fees"
then realising it's actually MORE fees,
but just for you in particular.
The frustration which was
simmering was now at a boiling point.
But, that wasn't the only problem.
Upwork had another issue, and unfortunately,
this one was baked in from the beginning.
If you've watched this far,
you might like our videos.
We do a lot of deep dives into tech
companies, so consider subscribing!
If we look at Upwork's revenue, we can
see great growth during the pandemic.
Almost $700 million in 2023.
But as we all know, the remote
work boom didn't really last.
In Q1 2026, revenue grew year over year by… 1%.
That's not a decline, but just 1%
growth signals a mature market.
Stagnation, maturity, and soon: decline.
The growth stage was over.
So on May 7, 2026, Upwork announced a
restructuring plan that included cutting
its workforce by approximately
24%, around 145 jobs out of 600.
About a quarter of the whole company! Yikes.
But something else was happening. Something worse.
Upwork was one of few platforms in the
freelance world. But after the pandemic
boom, that was different.
After remote work exploded,
more and more platforms began to pop up.
Many with better, more transparent pricing.
Some more niche for specific
industries. So, many freelancers left.
Or at least, they stopped signing up to Upwork.
In 2018 Upwork was "currently taking advantage of
the lack of competition in this market."
It wasn't the best place to find work,
but it was one of the only places.
But, Upwork was now worse than ever.
"All of my Upwork career I've been
cautious about getting a bad review
because of Upwork's horrendous appeal
system. Then they increased fees. And now
I can't even talk to a potential client who
has literally shown INTEREST in my services
by clicking on my profile and inviting me."
"Over the past few months, I submitted proposals
to around 150 jobs. I also saved many of those
projects in my favourites so I could check them
later. After checking them again, I found that
only around 30 jobs actually hired someone."
"Upwork proposals are not
even getting viewed in 2026."
All of which made all the
new platforms more appealing.
And AI is only making things worse.
Since ChatGPT's launch, freelance writing job
postings have fallen by roughly 30%. On Upwork,
writing projects were down
32% year-over-year in 2025.
The entry-level work that once formed the backbone
of the platform has been gutted, and with all
the weird fees weighing on freelancers, it's
understandable to see why Upwork might be dying.
The outlook for Upwork isn't great.
Market cap is near an all-time low.
Its price-to-earnings ratio sits around 9,
suggesting investors aren't
expecting much growth from here.
They are profitable now, but their GAAP net
income is already down 17% year over year.
So even after all that squeezing, future
prospects aren't looking too good.
Inside the platform, active clients
have been declining since 2025.
They've annoyed all their core customers,
and with their current pricing, I think
they'll slowly decline as people move to better
platforms. And that's probably for the best.
They're not the only ones though. Fiverr has
experienced a similar decline, though theirs
is far more dramatic, and weirder. Scandal
after scandal, huge debt chasing growth in
the pandemic, and a weird obsession with AI.
Click here to learn the rest of the story.